Has everybody got a copy of the agenda?
Would you mind taking minutes John?
Not at all.
Good. Well, then let's get started.
First of all, thank you everyone for attending
at short notice.
As you know, the objective of this meeting
of the Capital Works Committee is to discuss
a proposal for some urgent building work at
our Southside plant. As we've got to reach
a decision which may involve spending, we'll
run it as a formal meeting.
Now, you've read the proposal, so without
further ado, I'd like to open it up for discussion.
Perhaps if we can start with you Tan - what's
your view?
Well, I'm not convinced that the work is as
urgent as this report suggests, so perhaps
we should
So, to sum up, I think we are all aware that
some urgent work does need to be done, and
we will need to work on a longer term plan
for a major refit.
Well, if there's no more discussion, we'll
put it to a vote. We're recommending that
tenders be called for the urgent work needed.
All those in favour?
All those against?
Then that's agreed. Any other business?
Then we'll close the meeting. Thank you everyone.
The next meeting will be in two weeks, at
the same time.
Meetings. We love them or hate them - but
we have to have them. Of course there are
many different kinds of meetings, from an
informal chat, to a board meeting, or even
an Annual General Meeting - and some are more
formal than others - and so the language used
in them changes.
Today we're looking at a more formal meeting
and in particular at the role of the chairperson
- or the person who runs the meeting.
Our Chairperson is Denise. Let's look at how
she starts things off.
Has everybody got a copy of the agenda?
Would you mind taking minutes John?
Not at all.
Good. Well then, let's get started.
Denise first makes sure everyone has an agenda
- or a list of the items to be discussed at
the meeting.
Then she asks someone to take minutes - or
keep a record of the meeting. Then she announces
the start of the meeting - she officially
begins it.
Let's practise some useful phrases for these
three purposes.
Has everybody got a copy of the agenda?
Does everyone have an agenda?
Everybody should have received an agenda.
Would you mind taking minutes John?
Could somebody take the minutes please?
Well, then let's get started.
What does the chairperson do after formally
beginning the meeting?
First of all, thank you everyone for attending
at short notice. As you know, we needed to
convene this meeting of the Capital Works
committee to discuss a proposal for some urgent
building work at our Southside plant. As we've
got to reach a decision which may involve
spending, we'll run it as a formal meeting.
Now, you've all read the proposal, so without
further ado, I'd like to open it up for discussion.
Did you notice the different parts of that
introduction by the chairperson?
First, she thanked people for attending the
meeting. Even though it may be their job,
it's good practice to thank people for attending.
First of all, thank you everyone for attending
at short notice.
Next, Denise states the objective of the meeting.
Of course a meeting may have more than one
objective, but often meetings have one main
objective, or aim.
The Chair should state the objective of the
meeting. In this case it is to discuss a proposal,
and to reach a decision. A proposal is simply
a more formal word for a suggestion, but it
is usually a detailed suggestion, in a written
form.
Let's look at some different ways of stating
the objective of a meeting:
The objective of today's meeting is to discuss
the proposal
We're here today to discuss a proposal
The purpose of our meeting today is to discuss
the following proposal
The next job of the chair is to invite discussion.
Let's look at how Denise does this:
Now, you've all read the proposal, so without
further ado, I'd like to open it up for discussion.
Perhaps if we can start with you Tan - what's
your view?
Denise says, "Without further ado, I'd like
to open it up for discussion".
"Without further ado" just means without any
more procedure. We're going to discuss it
straight away. Then she says, "I'd like to
open it up for discussion."
'It' refers to the proposal she has just outlined.
Try repeating this phrase after me:
Let's open it up for discussion.
Let's open it up for discussion
Okay. Now, you can open a topic for general
discussion - which means anyone can have a
say. The Chairperson controls the discussion.
Or, the Chairperson may invite particular
people to speak. This is what Denise does
- watch again:
Perhaps if we can start with you Tan - what's
your view?
Denise invites Tan to start the discussion.
Let's practise a few phrases for asking someone
to speak.
Who'd like to start the discussion?
What's your view Tan?
Let's hear from Tan.
Do you have a view on this Tan?
Another job for the Chair is to summarise
the discussion - that is, concisely state
the main points made during the meeting.
So, to sum up, I think we are all aware that
some urgent work does need to be done, and
we will need to work on a longer term plan
for a major refit.
Denise summarises the main points from the
discussion. To introduce this she could use
various phrases. Practise these:
To sum up
In summary
So the main points are
The outcome of a meeting might be a suggestion
for an action. Depending on what kind of meeting
it is, this could be called a motion, or a
recommendation. In our example, Denise puts
the recommendation of the meeting to a vote.
Well, if there's no more discussion, let's
put the recommendation to a vote. We're recommending
tenders be called for the urgent work needed.
All those in agreement?
Anyone against?
Then that's agreed. Any other business?
Then we'll close the meeting. Thank you everyone.
The next meeting will be in two weeks, at
the same time.
Notice how Denise controls the meeting. She
doesn't say, "Is there any more discussion?"
She says, "If there's no more discussion,
we'll put it to a vote." She is controlling
the meeting by moving on. She then reiterates,
or re-states the recommendation and calls
for votes by saying, "All those in favour"
- that is, those who agree, and "All those
against". Votes are only taken in a formal
meeting procedure. In a less formal procedure,
a decision can be taken by consensus - by
everyone agreeing during the discussion.
Notice that after the vote, Denise says, "Then
that's agreed." A meeting agrees, or doesn't
agree to a recommendation. If it's a more
formal motion, we say the motion is carried
or not carried.
Often at the end of the meeting a chairperson
will call for any other business, before they
officially announce the meeting is closed,
and announce the time for the next meeting.